Bye-bye.
再見
I just got reservations at Michelle's...
我在米雪餐廳訂好位子了…
and tickets to The Music Man to celebrate...
還有《音樂人》的票來慶祝…
our first holiday as a betrothed couple.
我們成為訂婚夫妻後 第一個正式的節日
-"Betrothed." -Betrothed couple.
-「訂婚」 -訂婚夫妻
-Hi. -Hi.
-嘿！ -嗨！
Phoebe?
菲比？
Skull?
骷髏頭？
Yeah, it's my mom's.
是啊，是我媽的
Oh, my God!
我的天！
No, no, no. It's not my mom.
不，不，不，不是我媽
It belonged to my mom.
是屬於我媽的
She used to put it out every Christmas...
她以前每次耶誕節都會拿出來…
to remind us that even though it's Christmas, people still die.
要我們記得即使是耶誕節 人還是會死的
And you can put candy in it.
可以放糖果在裡面
Licorice?
吃糖？
Sure.
好啊
-I get Ben for the holidays this year. -That's great!
-今年班和我一起過節 -太好了！
-Are you gonna dress up as Santa? -Nope.
-你要扮成耶誕老公公嗎？ -不
I know Susan does every year.
我知道蘇珊每年都這麼做…
I want to take this year to teach him about Hanukkah.
可是今年我想教他瞭解光明節
And maybe I could teach Ben...
也許我能教班…
about the Christmas skull and how people die.
有關耶誕骷髏頭和人怎麼死亡
You may need to use this year to teach Ben about Phoebe.
你可以在今年教班認識菲比
嘿
-Did you know he was in there? -No.
-你知道他在裡面嗎？ -不知道
-How long have we been home? -About half an hour.
-我們回來多久了？ -大概半小時
Lovely.
好極了
The One With The Holiday Armadillo
本集播出：佳節犰狳
rainystar壓制iPod-MP4
（中央公園咖啡廳）
You know what I was thinking? When we get married, will you...
你知道我在想什麼？ 我們結婚後，你要不要…
change your name to "Bing"?
改掛夫姓「賓」？
No.
不要
Why not?
為什麼不？
Bing's weird.
「賓」很奇怪
Oh, hey, you guys.
你們好
My landlord just called. My apartment's gonna be ready soon.
猜猜怎麼著，我房東剛通知我 我的房子快好了
I guess I'll be moving out.
我很快就會搬出去了
Phoebe, I'm gonna miss you.
菲比，我會想念你的
Yes, you will be very sad.
是啊，你會很傷心
-I gotta go tell Rachel the good news. -You'll be living together again?
-我要告訴瑞秋這個好消息 -你們要再一起住？
-Why not? -She's having so much fun with Joey...
-是啊，為什麼不？ -她和喬伊住得很開心…
I assumed she'd still be living with him.
我以為她還會 繼續和他住在一起
Why do you think she's having so much fun?
為什麼你認為 她和喬伊住得很開心？
No reason, except she...
沒為什麼，只是...
told me.
她這麼說
She said she didn't want to live with me?
真的？她說她不要和我住？
No. No, she didn't say that.
沒有，她沒這麼說
I think you should talk to Monica now.
我想你該和摩妮卡說話了
Phoebe, I'm sure she wants to live with you.
菲比，別擔心 我確定她想和你住的
You're absolutely sure?
你確定？你很肯定？
No, but I'll bet she probably does.
不，我打賭她大概會
Oh, probably?
大概？
I don't like that word.
我不喜歡這個字
I know what "probably" really means. Yeah, yeah.
我知道「大概」真正的意思 是啊，是啊
"Oh, your mom probably won't kill herself."
「你媽大概不會自殺」
I'm sorry, but I'm not hanging my hopes...
對不起，我不要把我和瑞秋…
of Rachel and I living together on "probably."
住在一起的希望寄托在「大概」上面
You gotta take care of yourself in this world.
人在這世上要自己照顧自己
History teaches us nothing.
歷史教訓完全沒用
Bing doesn't seem so weird now,  does it?
「賓」現在不是那麼奇怪了吧？
You're home.
太好了，你在家
Guess what Phoebe got me for Christmas?
猜猜菲比送我什麼耶誕禮物
-Drums? -No, drums!
-鼓？ -不，鼓！
Could we get two burritos to go, please?
請給我們兩個墨西哥卷外帶
I'm sorry. But not that sorry, you don't have to live with it.
抱歉，不過沒那麼抱歉 因為你不用和他在一起生活
We have a reservation under Bing.
我們用錢德賓的名字訂了位子
Okay, we'll have a table for you in about 45 minutes.
好的，大約再45分鐘
45 minutes? We have tickets to The Music Man at 8.
45分鐘？《音樂人》的票是8點的
I'm sorry. Christmas is a very busy time, sir.
抱歉，耶誕節是最忙的時候
Is this because of the burrito thing?
這是因為墨西哥卷的玩笑嗎？
-You need to give him money. -Give him money? It was a joke!
-要給他錢 -給他錢？那只是個玩笑！
To get a table. Places like this are always shaking you down.
不，為了我們的位子 這種地方都是死要錢的
-Everybody wants a payoff. -All right, calm down, O'Malley.
-每個人都要小費 -好，鎮靜下來
-I'll slip him some money. -But you've got to be smooth.
-我會塞錢給他 -可是要不著痕跡
Hey, I can be smooth.
嘿，我可以不著痕跡
We're in a hurry. If you could get us a table...
我們有點趕時間 如果可以讓我們早一點…
a bit quicker, I'd appreciate it.
排到位子，我會很感激
-Of course, sir. -Okay.
-當然，先生 -好
-How'd it go? -Had the money in the wrong hand.
-怎麼樣？ -錢在另一隻手裡
You don't feel...
你會不會…
-Like you're gonna throw up? -No.
-想吐？ -不會
Well, I do. So let's...
我會，我們…
So, Ben, you...
班，你…
You know what holiday is coming up?
你知道快過節了，對不對？
Christmas.
耶誕節
Yeah, and you know what other holiday is coming up?
對，你知道另一個節日也要到了？
Christmas Eve.
耶誕夜
Yes, but also...
對，但…
Hanukkah!
光明節也是！
See, you're part Jewish and Hanukkah is a Jewish holiday.
你是一半猶太人 光明節是猶太人的節日
Santa has reindeers that can fly.
耶誕老公公有會飛的縻鹿
Right, but on Hanukkah..
對，但在光明節…
Hanukkah is a celebration of a miracle.
光明節是慶祝一個奇跡
Years and years ago there were these people called the Maccabees.
很多年前，有一群人叫做□加伯人
Okay, that's right. Yes...
好，對，是的…
but on Hanukkah, we sing:
但在光明節，我們唱的是：
Okay, it's not a contest.
好，這不是比賽
When is Santa coming?
耶誕老公公什麼時候來？
How about this year,  instead of Santa...
這樣好不好，今年我們 不要耶誕老公公…
we have fun celebrating Hanukkah?
我們來慶祝光明節？
No Santa?
沒有耶誕老公公？
Was I bad?
我不乖嗎？
No, no, no, you weren't bad. You've been very good, Ben.
不，不，你沒有不乖 你今年很乖，班
-Santa's mad at me. -No, hey, hey, come on.
-耶誕老公公生我的氣 -不是，嘿，嘿
Ben, Santa is not mad at you, okay?
班，耶誕老公公 沒有生你的氣，好嗎？
You're his favorite little guy.
你是他最喜歡的小孩
So Santa's coming?
耶誕老公公會來囉？
Yes!
對！
Santa's coming.
耶誕老公公會來
It's easy. Just keep it casual.
很簡單，保持輕鬆
Shake his hand and give him the money.
說句好話，和他握手，塞錢給他
-How do you know so much about this? -I don't know.
-你怎麼這麼瞭解？ -我不知道
Richard used to do it, didn't he?
理查以前常這麼做，是不是？
We'd be eating our soup right now.
我們現在可能已經在喝湯了
Mustached bastard.
可惡的小鬍子
Those people just left. Come on. Quick, give him the money.
這些人剛走，快，給他錢
Excuse me.
對不起
我們趕時間，可不可以…？
So you like the drums.
你喜歡鼓
That's great.
真好
I was worried that they would create maybe...
我本來還擔心它們會造成…
an unbearable living situation.
無法忍耐的居住狀況
But, okay, well, apparently not. So, yay!
好吧，看來沒有，好！
Hey, we already learned a song.
菲比，我們學會了一首歌
Ready? One, two, three, four.
準備好了？1，2，3，4
Tequila!
塔奇拉！
That's fun.
真好玩
Here you go.
來了
Thank you, Gunther. Put her there.
謝謝，阿甘，放在這裡
Definitely not easier with coins.
用銅板沒有更容易些
-Thank you. -Thank you.
-謝謝 -謝謝
Hey, Phoebe.
-菲比 -嘿
Here. Now I only owe you $49.50.
給你，現在我欠你49塊半
Hey, Phoebe...
菲比…
if you want to get Joey a gift that disrupts the entire building...
如果你要送喬伊 毀掉整棟樓的耶誕禮物…
why not something more subtle...
何不送更微妙一點的…
Like a wrecking ball...
像是鐵錘…
or a vial of small pox to release in the hallway?
或是天花病毒散播在走廊上？
It's not just the drum noise. Every five minutes...
不只是鼓的聲音，每5分鐘…
Joey throws his sticks in the air...
喬伊把鼓棒丟到空中…
and I have to hear: "Oh, my eye! Oh, God, my eye!"
然後我就會聽到： 「我的眼睛！我的眼睛！」
-I mean, it's so annoying. -Yes, thank you.
-煩死人了 -謝謝你
You see, this is how normal people are supposed to react to drums.
你看，這是正常人對鼓的反應
You got Joey drums to annoy Rachel...
菲比，你送喬伊鼓是為了煩瑞秋…
so she wouldn't want to live there anymore?
讓她不想繼續住在那裡？
Maybe on some level.
可能有一點
You could just not throw the sticks up in the air.
喬伊，你知道你不用丟鼓棒的
What is rock 'n' roll about that?
那怎麼能算是搖滾樂呢？
Hey, Joey, I got you another present.
喬伊，送你另一個禮物
Hold it! Before you tell me what it is...
等一下！先不要告訴我是什麼…
Okay, what is it?
是什麼？
It's a...
是一隻…
tarantula!
毒蜘蛛！
God, Rachel, I'm sorry. What was I thinking...
瑞秋，抱歉，我在想什麼…
giving Joey this big, gross,  scary spider...
送喬伊這麼一個 噁心的，可怕的蜘蛛…
in such a poorly constructed cage?
還用這麼一個鬆散的籠子？
What are you talking about? I love them.
你在說什麼？我喜歡它
I had a tarantula when I was a kid. But it died because my cat ate it.
我小時候就有一隻 後來我的貓咪吃掉了它
And then my cat died.
然後貓咪死了
But, Joey, isn't this cool?
喬伊，這不是很酷嗎？
Is it on me? I feel like it's on me. I got..
在我身上嗎？ 我覺得它在我身上，我…
Oh, isn't that adorable?
不是很可愛嗎？
Joey is afraid of the tarantula.
喬伊怕蜘蛛
He's so adorable.
他好可愛呦
He's so much fun.
老天，他很好玩
I'm glad you're having so much fun here.
喬伊是最棒的 很高興你在這裡住得很開心
Wait a minute.
等一下
What's the matter?
怎麼回事？
Our apartment is ready.
我們的房子好了
And that makes you angry because...?
你不高興因為…？
Because you'd rather live here with Joey.
因為你比較想和喬伊住在這裡
-Where did you get that? -Monica and Chandler...
-你為什麼這麼想？ -摩妮卡和錢德…
said you were having so much fun here...
說你和喬伊住得很開心…
and apparently no amount of drums or tarantula is gonna change that.
而且不管是鼓還是毒蜘蛛 都不會改變這點
Did you get all this stuff for Joey...
菲比，你送喬伊這些東西…
to try to drive me out of the apartment?
是要讓我不想住在這裡？
You might as well have gotten him a fish.
你還不如送他一條魚
You know how fish freak me out.
你知道我有多怕魚
Fish.
魚
But it wouldn't have mattered. We're gonna live together.
這些都不重要，我們會一起住的
We're roommates. That's the deal.
我們是室友，講好的
Yes, but I wanted you to want to live with me.
對，可是我希望你想和我一起住
But if you're having so much fun over here..
可是如果你在這裡住得這麼開心…
It's so much more fun with you.
和你在一起更開心
-We did have fun, didn't we? -We did.
-我們住一起時很開心，是不？ -對啊，好玩得不得了
They say, if we want,  we could see it tonight.
他們說如果要的話，今晚可以去看
-I would love to. -Yay, okay!
-好啊 -好，好！
-Good, good, good. -Great. All right. Good.
-好，好 -好
And Monica asked me to make the drumming stop.
摩妮卡要我停止鼓聲
Done.
好了
（萬聖節探險，面具大師）
Hello, sir. You here to return those pants?
你好，要退還那件褲子嗎？
No, these are my pants.
不，這是我的褲子
Okay.
是
-How can I help you? -Do you have a Santa outfit left?
-需要什麼？ -還有沒有耶誕老公公衣服？
Two days before Christmas? Sorry, man.
耶誕節前兩天？抱歉
Okay, look. Do you have anything Christmas-y?
好吧，有沒有什麼 比較算是耶誕節的？
I promised my son, and I really don't want to disappoint him.
我答應了我兒子，不想讓他失望
Come on, you gotta have something.
你們一定有的
I'm the Holiday Armadillo!
我是佳節犰狳！
I'm a friend of Santa's...
我是耶誕老公公的朋友…
and he sent me here to wish you...
他要我來祝你…
a merry Christmas!
耶誕快樂！
What happened to Santa, Holiday Armadillo?
耶誕老公公怎麼了，佳節犰狳？
Santa was unavailable...
耶誕老公公沒有空…
so close to Christmas.
在這麼接近耶誕節的時候
Come in, have a seat.
請進，請坐
You must be exhausted, coming all the way from Texas.
你一定累壞了，大老遠從德州跑來
-Texas? -That's right, Ben.
-德州？ -對，班
I'm Santa's representative...
我是耶誕老公公的…
for all the Southern states.
西南州代表
And Mexico!
還有墨西哥！
But Santa sent me here...
耶誕老公公要我來這裡…
to give you these presents, Ben.
送禮物給你
Maybe the lady will help me with these presents.
這位小姐可以幫我拿禮物
Wow, thanks!
謝謝！
You're welcome, Ben.
不客氣，班
Merry Christmas.
耶誕快樂
And happy Hanukkah!
光明節快樂！
Are you for Hanukkah too? Because I'm part Jewish.
你也為光明節而來嗎？ 因為我是一半猶太人
You are? Me too.
你是？我也是
Because armadillos also wandered in the desert?
因為犰狳也在沙漠裡晃蕩？
You want to wander in the hall?
你想在走廊晃蕩嗎？
Hey, Ben!
班！
What if the Holiday Armadillo...
佳節犰狳…
told you all about the Festival of Lights?
跟你說光之節的故事好嗎？
Cool!
酷！
Come on, Ben.
來，班
Years and years ago...
很多年以前…
there were these people called...
有一群人，叫做…
-the Maccabees! -Ho, ho, ho!
-□加伯人！ -呵！呵！呵！
Merry Christmas!
耶誕快樂！
Santa!
-耶誕老公公！ -嘿！
What are you doing here, Santa?
你來幹什麼，耶誕老公公？
Well, I'm here to see my old buddy, Ben.
我來看我的老朋友班
What are you doing here...
你在這兒幹什麼…
Weird Turtle Man?
怪烏龜人？
I'm the Holiday Armadillo...
我是佳節犰狳…
your part-Jewish friend.
你的半猶太人朋友
You sent me here to give Ben some presents.
你要我來送禮物給班
Remember?
記得嗎？
What?
什麼？
Did you bring me any presents, Santa?
耶誕老公公，你有帶禮物給我嗎？
You bet I did, Ben.
當然有，班
Put her there.
放在這裡
Well, it would have worked this time if his hands weren't so damn small.
如果不是他的手太小，會成功的
Ho, ho, ho!
呵！呵！呵！
Ben, come open more gifts.
班，來開禮物
The armadillo and I will have a talk in the kitchen.
耶誕老公公，佳節犰狳和我 要在廚房談一談
There's a sentence I never thought I'd say.
我絕對想不到會說出這句話
What are you doing?
你在幹什麼？
You said you were having trouble finding a Santa costume...
你告訴每個人說 你找不到耶誕老公公衣服…
so I borrowed one from a guy at work.
所以我向同事借了一件
Thank you, but you gotta leave.
謝謝，你必須離開
-Why? -Because...
-為什麼？ -因為…
I'm finally getting him excited about Hanukkah...
我終於讓他對光明節有興趣…
and you're wrecking it.
而你正在破壞
But I didn't get to shake my belly like a bowlful of jelly.
可是我還沒搖我的勝子呢
I'm sorry, Chandler, but this is really important to me.
抱歉，錢德，這對我很重要
Fine, I'll give the suit back.
好，我去還這件衣服
Hey, you think you can keep it another night?
你可以再多借一晚嗎？
Santa, really?
耶誕老公公？真的？
Yeah, is that okay?
是啊，可以嗎？
Did your dad ever dress up like Santa?
你爸有扮過耶誕老公公嗎？
-No. -Then it's okay!
-沒有 -那就可以！
Okay, Ben. Santa has to go.
班，耶誕老公公要走了
Say goodbye.
說再見
No, why does he have to go?
不要，他為什麼要走？
Because if Santa and the Holiday...
因為耶誕老公公和佳節…
Armadillo...
犰狳…
are ever in the same room for too long...
如果在同一個房子裡太久…
the universe will implode!
宇宙會爆炸！
Merry Christmas!
耶誕快樂！
No, why can't the armadillo leave? I want Santa.
不要，為什麼不是犰狳走呢？ 我要耶誕老公公
Fine, I give up. Santa..
好，我放棄，耶誕老公公…
Santa can stay!
耶誕老公公可以留下來！
Well, I'll stay...
我留下來…
but only because I want to hear about Hanukkah.
因為我想聽光明節的故事
Ben, will you sit here with Santa...
班，你要不要和耶誕老公公…
and learn about Hanukkah?
一起坐下來聽光明節的故事？
Okay, Santa.
好的
-Thank you. -You're welcome.
-謝謝 -不客氣
All right, it's time...
好，來聽…
for the story of Hanukkah.
光明節的故事
Years and years ago...
很多年以前…
there were these people called the Maccabees!
有一群人叫□加伯人！
Merry Christmas!
耶誕快樂！
Oh, wow, look at this place!
看看這地方！
Oh, this is terrible.
真糟糕
They've made so many changes...
他們改了很多…
I can't even feel my grandmother's presence anymore.
我感受不到我祖母的存在
Oh, new sconces!
新的燭台！
-Oh, my God! -What?
-我的天！ -怎麼？
Remember how you told me your grandmother put up that wall...
記得你告訴我你祖母要做一道牆…
-to make that into two bedrooms? -Yeah.
-來隔成兩間房？ -對
And that the landlord might find out...
房東可能會發現…
-and then tear it down? -Yeah?
-把它拆了？ -對？
Do you really not know where I'm going?
你真的不知道我說這些的原因？
It left. It's one huge room.
牆沒有了，是一間大房間
Oh, no!
哦，不！
Wow!
哇！
See?
看到了？
I guess we'll have to put the wall back up.
我們必須要把牆弄回來
-You can't, with the new skylight. -There's a skylight?
-不行，因為新的天窗 -有天窗？
Wow!
哇！
So should we start looking for a new place?
我們該怎麼辦？要開始找新地方嗎？
You know, I'm sensing...
我感到…
that my grandmother would not be comfortable with that.
我祖母可能不喜歡那樣
Oh, yeah?
是嗎？
Starting to feel her again there,  are we?
又能感覺到她了，是嗎？
-A little bit. Yeah. -Yeah.
-有一點，對 -是
Is your grandmother maybe saying that you should live here alone?
菲比，你祖母是不是說 你應該一個人住這裡？
You heard it too? You have the gift.
你也聽見了？你有天份
Phoebe, it's okay.
菲比，沒關係
I like living with Joey.
我喜歡和喬伊住
-Are you sure? -Please. I hate packing...
-你確定嗎？ -拜託，我討厭打包…
it's closer to work.
那裡離公司比較近
And we do have fun.
我們在一起很開心
Although, I'm really gonna miss living with you.
雖然我真的會想念和你住在一起
-Oh, me too. -I know.
-我也是 -我知道
Did you hear that?
等一下，你有沒有聽到？
I'm getting something from your grandmother.
聽，我聽到你祖母說話
She said since you get to keep the one-bedroom apartment...
她說既然你要一個人住這裡…
you should give Rachel the purple chair.
你該把那把紫色椅子給瑞秋
No, I do not hear that.
沒有，我沒有聽到
And the miracle was that that little bit of oil...
奇跡在於那一點點的油…
that should have lasted just one day, burned for....
應該只夠燒一天的，卻燒了…
-Eight whole days. -That's right.
-整整8天 -對
And that's why we celebrate Hanukkah today. The end.
這就是為什麼我們 今天慶祝光明節，故事完結
-Awesome. -Yeah.
-好棒 -是啊
My favorite part...
我最喜歡的部份…
was when Superman flew all the Jews out of Egypt.
是超人救出全埃及的猶太人
The armadillo was actually not so thrilled about that part.
犰狳不是那麼喜歡那部份
Okay, Ben, it's time to light...
班，該來點…
the Hanukkah candles!
光明節蠟燭！
嘿
Wow! Looks like the Easter Bunny's funeral in here.
哇！好像是復活節兔子的葬禮
Come on, come on. We're lighting the candles.
來，來，我們要點蠟燭
I understand why Superman is here...
我瞭解為什麼超人在這裡…
but why is there a porcupine at the Easter Bunny's funeral?
但為什麼有豪豬 參加復活節兔子的葬禮？
-You get it? -I got it.
-你弄好了嗎？ -弄好了
Back in the cage?
它進籠子了沒？
It's back in the cage.
它在籠子裡了
Is the cage closed?
籠子關好了嗎？
Joey, will you just come out here and stop being such a baby!
喬伊，出來好嗎？ 別像個小孩一樣！